Yuri Dolzhneko

Tech lead / Full stack software engineer

Born 19 December, 1984

Nationality: Dutch

Fritz Dietrich Kahlenbergstraat, 133 | 1087 LL, Amsterdam | The Netherlands

+31 (o) 634883558 | yuri.dolzhenko@gmail.com

Summary

Tech lead / full stack software engineer with about 10 years of experience in designing, developing and maintaining software solutions for large international businesses.

Buzzwords

Lots of Java and JVM languages on a backend. Legacy systems, microservices, monoliths, refactoring of those. RESTful and GraphQL APIs. Spring framework and everything that comes with it. Data centers on premises, AWS and Pivotal Cloud Foundry. A bit of data analytics using map-reduce, R and some other fancy tools. SQL or NOSQL databases - both may work, depending on a task to solve. Angular, Typescript, D3.js, Ext JS for creating user interfaces SPAs, PWAs or mobile applications. NPM, Maven, Gradle for managing dependencies and building things. Atlassian tools for managing projects and knowledge sharing. Git - for version control, Jenkins, CircleCI and GitLab for continuous integration and delivery, Docker - for portability and predictability, Kubernetes - for running things and scale them up and down. Sonar, JUnit, Mockito, Karma, Jasmine, Selenium to make sure things are reliable. Reactive and functional programming for efficiency and performance. Agile, scrum and devops for making this list complete.

Experience

• 2018 - present, KLM Royal Dutch Airlines, (http://www.klm.nl), The Netherlands

Tech lead, Consultant

In KLM I'm working in a team of around 10 people that builds software tools and solutions on demand by customers across the whole company—we do projects for cargo department, we help planning department with schedule and roastering for cockpit/cabin crews, we monitor disruptions and visualise data for maintenance. These solutions are meant to be built quickly from scratch in a truly agile manner, so users can start using them ASAP, while providing us with feed-

back about usage patterns and new requirements. We use Spring Boot to build backends, Angular/ Ionic to build user interfaces, we save data mostly to PostreSQL, we read it from many data sources, both very legacy and new. We deploy our software in Pivotal Cloud Foundry or on in-house Kubernetes cluster. I joined the team as a full stack developer and after some time became a technical lead. Currently besides development itself I'm responsible for coaching team members, short and long term planning of technical work and discussing requirements with our old and new (happy) customers.

• 2017 - 2018, Randstad, (http://www.randstad.nl), The Netherlands

Senior full stack developer, Consultant

In Randstad, I helped the company with migration of its systems from the on-premises data centers to the AWS. The goal was not only lift things and move them to another infrastructure, but eventually make applications cloud-native, so we could benefit from all tools AWS can offer. HR business can be difficult and that was exactly the case - we had lots of different frontends, apis and applications that uses all sorts of technologies and frameworks - some of them were old and ready to retire, some used RDBMS, some NOSQL. While migrating we still had to develop new features and maintain ones, and migration itself had been done as seamlessly as possible without customers and business people noticing anything.

• 2017 - present, LinkIT, (http://www.linkit.nl), The Netherlands

Consultant

I joined LinkIT, another consultancy company to participate in efforts to transform a classic consultancy bureau into company that combines traditional staffing and consultancy services with inhouse development of solutions for clients.

• 2014 - 2017, ING, (http://www.ing.nl), The Netherlands

Senior full stack developer, Consultant

In ING bank's IT department I helped with the bank's new omni-channel initiative (essentially same API endpoints serving data for all types of clients, from self-service portals for private and business customers to call centers and bank' branches). RESTful APIs that we built were bridges between Angular-powered frontends and TIBCO messaging infrastructure. I was part of one of many feature-teams consisted of product owner, frontend, backend and TIBCO developers

(typically around 5-9 people), so we could develop complete fully-functional solutions independently. Besides developing APIs themselves, I also worked on actual frontends that consumed data from APIs.

• 2014 - 2017, Qualogy, (http://www.qualogy.nl), The Netherlands

Consultant

After three years of working on the same product, I felt like I have to do something else, so I started to work for Qualogy as a consultant in 2014 to have an opportunity to work for different clients and solve different problems.

• **2011** - **2014**, Secondfloor (www.secondfloor.com), The Netherlands

Java developer

I had never thought about moving to the Netherlands, but today you never know where you will end up tomorrow. One of many Dutch recruitment companies reached me at LinkedIn and asked if I was interested in having an interview with one of theirs clients. «Why not?» - I replied. After a couple of talks I found myself packing stuff and moving to Amsterdam. Company was all about risk management, reporting and compliance tools for insurance and finance companies. There I worked on a product, jointly created by us and IBM (requirements were coming from IBM, we were working on the implementation, while IBM was selling the final product to their customers). It was a tool that was used for collection of structured and unstructured data, for reporting and decision making. Application was Spring-backed (MVC, security, JMS) and connected to Oracle or DB2 databases (using Hibernate for the most things and plain JDBC for some of them). It exposed a RESTful APIs for third-parties and for our own frontend that was built using Ext JS. We had a team of one project manager who did all the planning, three to seven developers to actually develop what was planned, couple of testers to test things and business analyst who was busy with writing specifications together with analysts from IBM. I was working on both backend and frontend parts of the application and busy with delivering binaries, fixing issues that came from testers in our test environments and supporting clients and real production systems.

• 2009-2011, Luxoft (http://www.luxoft.ru/), Russia

Senior java developer, lead java developer

Luxoft was (and, I guess, still is) one the biggest IT consultancy companies in eastern Europe, with the huge portfolio of clients, including Boeing, Deutsche Bank and UBS. I failed first interview there when I first came to Moscow and succeeded one year later. I joined one of the many development teams that company had on-site at UBS bank. We worked on application that was essentially a frontend to multiple bank's datasources with information about financial instruments. We had to replace old swing-based desktop solution that had performance issues with the new, web-based one (spring mvc, with freemarker templates and Jquery / Jquery UI on the frontend). We had four developers (all in Moscow), testing team in Bangalore, India and product owner in Boston, USA. We maintained and supported four instances of the application in four different regions (long before AWS showed up) and that guaranteed us lots of fun when it came to communication: catch up calls/meetings in the evenings because of Boston's time zone, bunches of issues every morning because of Bangalore's time zone. While working on the project, my responsibilities grew from just developing a new functionality and bug fixing to deploying releases to production, supporting customers and planning changes upfront.

• 2008-2009, Intouch Insurance (http://www.intouch.ru), Russia

Java developer

I moved to Moscow in pursuit of career opportunities - there weren't many things to do in my hometown. I immediately joined in-house development team of "Intouch Insurance", a pioneer company in online sales in Russia. Company was part of the international insurance group, so team was distributed between Moscow and Warsaw, so a lot of traveling, remote work and communication were involved. We were responsible for building and maintaining internal CRM system which covered all the business processes that are typical for insurance companies - policy sales, claims handling, payments management and etc. We had a pretty much typical web application for those days - JSP's, Struts servlets, Java EE's JDO to connect to Oracle database and a tiny bit of javascript on a frontend side.

• 2007-2008, Rostelecom (http://www.rostelecom.ru/), Russia

Java developer

I started my career as a java developer in the biggest Russian telecommunications company. There

I worked in a department responsible for a bunch of intranet applications used by company's different departments (HR, billing, etc). RPCs instead of RESTful APIs, Struts instead of Spring, pure JDBC instead of object-relational mapping tools, no continuous deployment or delivery. No Jira, agile, test driven development or devops just yet, but we were responsible for everything starting from initial design to production deployment and supporting of our users.

Education & certification

- 2001-2006, Mathematician, system programmer, master degree (Kuban State University, Krasnodar, Russia)
- 2012, MongoDB Developer (10 Gen training & certification)
- *2013, Certified Spring Professional (VMWare training & certification)
- 2018, AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (Amazon Web Services)